Finding Aid for George E. Brand papers, 1910-1963
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
George E. Brand papers 1910-1963
Brand, George E., 1888-1963.
85777 AC Aa 2
Detroit attorney; member and officer of the American Judicature Society, the American Bar Association, and the State Bar of Michigan; correspondence, organizational files, speeches, and scrapbooks.
3 linear feet
11 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of George E. Brand, Jr. (Donor no. 4035 ) and came to the library in 1963.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
George E. Brand was born in Houghton, Michigan on June 11, 1888. He was admitted to the Bar in Michigan in 1912 after receiving his LLB degree with honors from the University of Michigan Law School in 1912 where he associate editor of the Michigan Law Review (1911-1912).
In his career, Brand was both a practicing attorney and an active member of numerous legal professional associations. At different times he was president of both the State Bar of Michigan and the Detroit Bar Association, and from 1933 to 1938, he was a member of the Michigan Board of Law Examiners. On the national level he was active in the American Bar Association as a member of the Board of Governors, the House of Delegates and major committees. He also was president of the American Judicature Society and a regent of the American College of Trial Lawyers. Brand authored several books, including "Unauthorized Practice Decision" (1937) and "Bar Associations, Attorneys and Judges-Organization, Ethics, Discipline" (1956). He died on March 28, 1963.
The George E. Brand collection is arranged into the following series: Personal/biographical; American Bar Association; American Judicature Society; Michigan Bar Association; Other materials (including speeches, general correspondence and articles); University of Michigan Law School Class of 1912 materials; a photograph; and scrapbooks.
Subjects:
American Bar Association.; American Judicature Society.; Lawyers--Michigan--Detroit.; Michigan State Bar Association.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Law. Class of 1912.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Marston, George A., 1873-
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Personal/biographical
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
  - Personal correspondence (including letters of congratulations, thank you letters)
    - 1918-1938 (Box 1)
    - 1939-1947 (Box 1)
    - 1948-1963 (Box 1)
  - Law School student material; include research paper 1910 and record of expenses, 1911-1912. (Box 1)
- American Bar Association
  - Correspondence
    - 1941-1944 (Box 1)
    - January 1953-June 1958 (Box 1)
  - Professional Relations Committee 1954-1962, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Section on Bar Activities (Box 1)
  - Legal Education in Michigan (Box 1)
  - Survey of the legal profession (Box 1)
  - Campaign for ABA Presidency 1951-1954, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Judicial Selection
    - Tenure and compensation (general) (Box 1)
    - Editorials (Box 1)
    - Letters (Box 1)
    - Reports, reviews (Box 1)
    - Oklahoma Conference 1962 (Box 1)
    - Oklahoma Conference 1962 loose material (Box 1)
- American Judicature Society
  (George Brand was president 1945-1953)
  - Correspondence
    - 1952-1953 (Box 2)
    - January 1, 1954-December 31, 1957 (Box 2)
    - January 1, 1958-1962 (Box 2)
- Michigan Bar Association
  - Executive Committee minutes 1936-1938 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence
    - 1936 (Box 2)
    - 1945-1957 (Box 2)
    - 1958-1963 (Box 2)
  - Committee on International and Comparative Law, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Other materials
  - Scribes (Box 2)
  - General correspondence
    - May 1934-1949 (Box 2)
    - January 1950-February 1962 (Box 2)
  - Speeches and articles, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Speeches and articles, 6 folders (Box 3)
- University of Michigan Law School Class of 1912
  - 1947 Reunion (Box 3)
  - 1952, 1957, 1962 Reunions (Box 3)
  - Articles (Box 3)
  - Memorial fund (Box 3)
  - Directories and Accounts (Box 3)
  - Correspondence
    - 1916 (Box 3)
    - 1922-June 14, 1935 (Box 3)
    - March 1936-December 1946 (Box 3)
    - January 1947-1952 (Box 3)
    - 1953 (Box 3)
- Photographs
  - Portrait of George A. Marston (Box 3)
- Scrapbooks
  - Various dates, clippings and memorabilia (Volume 1)
  - Various dates, clippings and memorabilia (Volume 2)
    (continued)
  - Various dates, clippings and memorabilia (Volume 3)
  - Various dates, clippings and memorabilia (Volume 4)
  - Various dates, clippings and memorabilia (Volume 5)
  - Various dates, clippings and memorabilia (Volume 6)
  - Various dates, clippings and memorabilia (Volume 7)
  - Various dates, clippings and memorabilia (Volume 8)
  - Various dates, clippings and memorabilia (Volume 9)
  - Various dates, clippings and memorabilia (Volume 10)
  - Various dates, clippings and memorabilia (Volume 11)